A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of Francis X. Sutton FA568
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Ford Foundation History Project, Regional Files, 1951-1985; VI
  - Middle East and Africa -- Report, "Office for the Middle East and Africa Program Review and Funding Request for FY 1980-1981", 1979 July (Box 64, Folder 6)
  - Middle East and Africa -- Report, Ford Foundation Assistance in the Arab Middle East and North Africa, 1979 August (Box 64, Folder 7)
  - Middle East and Africa -- Report, "Agricultural Development in Tropical Africa and the Role of the Ford Foundation" by Haldore Hanson, 1984 November 2 (Box 64, Folder 8)
  - Middle East and Africa -- Review Conference -- Discussion Papers (folder 1 of 2), 1972 June (Box 64, Folder 9)
  - Middle East and Africa -- Review Conference -- Discussion Papers (folder 2 of 2), 1972 June (Box 64, Folder 10)
  - Middle East and Africa -- Trip Files -- Africa Trip Notes (Jun-Sep 1959) (folder 1 of 2), 1959 June-July (Box 64, Folder 11)
  - Middle East and Africa -- Trip Files -- Africa Trip Notes (Jun-Sep 1959) (folder 2 of 2), 1959 August-September (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - Middle East and Africa -- West Africa -- Nigeria -- Correspondence, Notes Re: Foundation Work, 1985 (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - Middle East and Africa -- West Africa -- Nigeria -- Dissertation Re: Ford Foundation Development of Nigerian University by Christiana Tamuno, 1983 (Box 65, Folder 3)
  - Middle East and Africa -- West Africa -- Nigeria -- Grant Funding -- Summaries and Grant List, 1963-1981 (Box 65, Folder 4)
  - Middle East and Africa -- West Africa -- Nigeria -- Public Service Review Commission and Ford Foundation Support, 1972-1976 (Box 79, Folder 6)
  - Middle East and Africa -- West Africa -- Nigeria -- Report, "The Ford Foundation and Public Management in Nigeria" by Stephanie Warren and Clark Bloom, 1963 June 15 (Box 65, Folder 5)
  - Middle East and Africa -- West Africa -- Nigeria -- Reports, Proposals Re: International Institute of Tropical Agriculture, 1963-1982 (Box 65, Folder 6)
  - Middle East and Africa -- West Africa -- Trip Files -- Sutton Trip for History Fact Gathering -- Correspondence, Notes, Agendas, Reports, Grant Lists, 1984 (Box 65, Folder 7)
  - Middle East and Africa -- West Africa -- Trip Files -- Report on Trip to Guinea (Apr 1-3, 1985) by Richard Horovitz, 1985 April 19 (Box 65, Folder 8)
  - Middle East and Africa -- United Arab Republic -- Egypt -- Annual Program Expenditures/Grants List, 1981 (Box 65, Folder 9)
  - Middle East and Africa -- United Arab Republic -- Egypt -- Report Re: Ford Foundation Grants to American University in Cairo, 1984 November (Box 65, Folder 10)
  - Middle East and Africa -- United Arab Republic -- Egypt -- Grant Proposal, Evaluations, Reports Re: Egypt's Institute of National Planning, 1959-1980 (Box 65, Folder 11)
  - Middle East and Africa -- United Arab Republic -- Memorandum Re: Recent Developments in the UAR, 1961 September 12 (Box 65, Folder 12)
  - Middle East and Africa -- United Arab Republic -- Reference/Background Materials on United Arab Republic, 1968-1984 (Box 65, Folder 13)
  - Middle East and Africa -- United Arab Republic -- Report, "Manpower Resources in Economic Development" by John T. Hilliard, 1961 June (Box 65, Folder 14)
  - Middle East and Africa -- United Arab Republic -- Report, "The Ford Foundation in the United Arab Republic: Information for Consultants", 1963 (Box 65, Folder 15)
  - Middle East and Africa -- United Arab Republic -- Report, "Position Paper on the American University in Cairo" by James T. Ivy, 1969 September 22 (Box 65, Folder 16)
  - Middle East and Africa -- United Arab Republic -- Trip Files -- Sutton and Donald Kingsley Visit to Cairo Field Office (Nov 1969) -- Agenda, UAR Program Review, Grant Reports (Box 65, Folder 17)
- Ford Foundation History Project, Subject Files, 1949-1985; VII
  The Ford Foundation History Project Subject Files include correspondence, memoranda, grant proposals, reports, meeting materials, and notes. The History Project Subject Files document the Foundation's broad-based, issue-focused efforts aimed at education and educational reform, international studies and relations, development planning and management, and arts and culture, among others. The Subject Files include program management materials, budget reports, and International Division administrative and operational files.
  Also within this series are the Ford Foundation internal history files outlined by Dr. Sutton in chapter and section order. These files contain notes and background information on the early history of the Foundation and the formation of its international programs. Biographical information on the Foundation's original trustees and staff, initial budgeting demands, program considerations and later developments shaped the structure of Dr. Sutton's history outline. The Sutton/McCarthy History Text Files consist of the chapters that Dr. Sutton and his research assistant, Nancy McCarthy, composed using the materials found within this series. Some of these chapters also double as independent Foundation reports.
  - Arts -- Materials for Arts Review -- Reports, Outlines, 1966-1981 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Arts -- Reports Re: Humanities and the Arts Division and Foundation Work, 1972 June (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - Arts -- Reports, Memoranda Re: Foundation Support of Arts and Culture Overseas, 1976-1980 (Box 66, Folder 3)
  - Arts -- Report, "The Arts and Culture in the Ford Foundation", 1981 June (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - Budget -- Foundation-Wide Proposed Budget, FY 1974-1975, 1973 June (Box 66, Folder 5)
  - Budget -- Foundation-Wide Proposed Budget, FY 1976-1977, 1975 June (Box 66, Folder 6)
  - Budget -- Foundation-Wide Proposed Budget, FY 1978-1979, 1977 June (Box 66, Folder 7)
  - Budget -- Report, "Choices Under a Reduced Program Budget", 1974 November (Box 66, Folder 8)
  - Budget -- Review Material -- "FY 1978-1979 Budget Planning: Program Alternatives and Options", 1977 March (Box 66, Folder 9)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Economic Planning and Advisory Programs -- Memoranda and Notes, 1968-1984 (Box 66, Folder 10)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Management and Business -- Grant Proposal, Memoranda Re: Al-Ahram Center for Political and Strategic Studies (Egypt), 1982 (Box 66, Folder 11)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Management and Business -- Indian Institute of Management, Ahmedabad (IIMA) -- Annual Report, Social Development Conference Agenda, Papers Re: Program Management, 1976-1982 (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Management and Business -- Report, "Training for Public Administration and Management in Developing Countries" by Samuel Paul, 1983 (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Memoranda, Notes, Reports Re: Public Administration, Training of Specialists and Additional Foundation Assistance, 1973-1974 (Box 67, Folder 3)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Political Development and Policy Making Initiatives -- Notes, Paper, 1971-1983 (Box 67, Folder 4)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Public Management Review Materials -- Memoranda, Notes, Reports, 1972-1975 (Box 67, Folder 5)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Report, "The Ford Foundation and Public Management in the Less-Developed Countries" by Francis X. Sutton and Theodore Smith, 1975 August 6 (Box 67, Folder 6)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Report, "Administration and Economic Planning in Eastern Africa" by Courtney Nelson, 1977 April (Box 67, Folder 7)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Report, "The Rise and Fall of Political Development" by Fred Riggs with Related Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 67, Folder 8)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Report, "The Role of Foundations in Development" by Francis X. Sutton, 1982 December (Box 67, Folder 9)
  - Development Planning and Management -- Reports Re: Post-Graduate Training Abroad by Robert Myers, undated (Box 67, Folder 10)
  - Education and Public Policy Division -- Program Reviews -- Background Material, 1981 January (Box 67, Folder 11)
  - Education and Research -- Cultural Development -- Memoranda, Notes, Grant Requests, Papers, etc. (1 of 3), 1968-1982 (Box 68, Folder 1)
  - Education and Research -- Cultural Development -- Memoranda, Notes, Grant Requests, Papers, etc. (2 of 3), 1968-1982 (Box 68, Folder 2)
  - Education and Research -- Cultural Development -- Memoranda, Notes, Grant Requests, Papers, etc. (3 of 3), 1968-1982 (Box 68, Folder 3)
  - Education and Research -- Grant Requests, 1967-1982 (Box 68, Folder 4)
  - Education and Research -- Memoranda Re: Institute of International Education Research Program, 1983-1984 (Box 68, Folder 5)
  - Education and Research -- Report, "The Land-Grant Colleges in International Affairs" by Forrest F. Hill, circa 1962 (Box 68, Folder 6)
  - Education and Research -- Report, "Education in the Developing Countries" by Forrest F. Hill, 1962 December (Box 68, Folder 7)
  - Education and Research -- Report, "America the Resilient" by F. Champion Ward, 1967 November (Box 68, Folder 8)
  - Education and Research -- Report, "Reflections on the 'Internationalizing' of Higher Education" by F. Champion Ward, 1974 March (Box 68, Folder 9)
  - Education and Research -- Report, "The Funding of International Cooperation in Higher Education, Scholarship and Research" by Francis X. Sutton, 1982 April 29 (Box 68, Folder 10)
  - Education and Research -- Report -- Manuscript, "The School and the University: An International Perspective" by Burton R. Clark (ed.) (1 of 2), 1984 February (Box 68, Folder 11)
  - Education and Research -- Report -- Manuscript -- "The School and the University: An International Perspective" by Burton R. Clark (ed.) (2 of 2), 1984 February (Box 68, Folder 12)
  - Education and Research -- Science and Technology -- Outline, Notes Re: Foundation's International Programs, 1983 (Box 68, Folder 13)
  - Education and Research -- Science and Technology -- Report, "Swimming for 25 Years as a Pilot Fish at the Ford Foundation" by Richard Magat, 1982 September (Box 68, Folder 14)
  - History General Files -- Bibliography -- Notes, Book Reviews, Index to Ford Foundation Reports, 1969-1985 (Box 69, Folder 1)
  - History General Files -- Correspondence Re: Ford Foundation History Reconnaisance, 1983-1984 (Box 69, Folder 2)
  - History General Files -- Ford Foundation Archives -- List of Ford Foundation Conference Papers, 1953-1980, 1985 (Box 69, Folder 3)
  - History General Files -- Foundations -- Organization and General Information, 1983 (Box 69, Folder 4)
  - History General Files -- History Project Proposal, Budget, Consultant Work, 1983-1984 (Box 69, Folder 5)
  - History General Files -- Interviews/Oral Histories for Ford Foundation History Project, A-L -- Summaries, Notes, Related Materials (1 of 2), 1980-1984 (Box 69, Folder 6)
  - History General Files -- Interviews/Oral Histories for Ford Foundation History Project, M-W -- Summaries, Notes, Related Materials (2 of 2), 1984 (Box 69, Folder 7)
  - History General Files -- Outlines, Progress Report, Memoranda Re: History Project, 1983-1986 (Box 69, Folder 8)
  - History General Files -- Related Studies -- Arnold Thackray and the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences -- Correspondence and Report, 1984 (Box 69, Folder 9)
  - History General Files -- Related Studies -- Ed Mason and the Harvard Institute for International Development -- Correspondence, Notes, Grant Listings, 1984 (Box 69, Folder 10)
  - History General Files -- Related Work -- Rockefeller Foundation Overseas Program -- Interview with Lindsley Kimball, 1955 April 1 (Box 69, Folder 11)
  - History General Files -- Trustees -- Biographies, Press Clippings, 1968-1983 (Box 69, Folder 12)
  - Internal History 1.1 -- The Founding -- Study Group and Follow-up by McPeak and Others, circa 1983 (Box 69, Folder 13)
  - Internal History 1.2 -- The Founding -- Initial Board Composition -- Notes Re: Trustees and Manuscript on Karl T. Compton, 1959-1983 (Box 69, Folder 14)
  - Internal History 1.3 -- The Founding -- Initial Staff and Delegation of Power -- Correspondence between Robert Hutchins and F. Champion Ward, 1954-1984 (Box 69, Folder 15)
  - Internal History 1.4 -- The Founding -- Initial Financial Situation -- Summary of Conversation with Eli Whitney Debevoise, 1984 March 2 (Box 69, Folder 16)
  - Internal History 2.1 -- Organization to 1966 -- The Board -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Organizational Chart of Officers, Summaries of Interviews, 1952-1985 (Box 69, Folder 17)
  - Internal History 2.2 -- Organization to 1966 -- Staff and Program Organization -- Ford Foundation Program Timeline, Memoranda, Notes, Staff Lists, Organizational Charts, Interview Summaries, 1954-1984 (Box 69, Folder 18)
  - Internal History 2.3 -- Organization to 1966 -- Field Offices -- List of Ford Foundation Field Offices, 1984 (Box 69, Folder 19)
  - Internal History 3.1 -- Organizational Evolution, 1966-1981 -- The Board -- List of Officers, Trustee Travel Information, Notes, Background Materials, 1984 (Box 69, Folder 20)
  - Internal History 3.2 -- Organizational Evolution, 1966-1981 -- Staff and Program Organization -- List of Program Officers, Notes (Box 69, Folder 21)
  - Internal History 3.3 -- Organizational Evolution, 1966-1981 -- Field Offices -- List of Overseas Offices, 1984 (Box 69, Folder 22)
  - Internal History 4 -- Financial and Statistical Record -- International Division Program Strategy -- Memoranda and Budget Projections, 1968 (Box 70, Folder 1)
  - Internal History 4 -- Financial and Statistical Record -- Foundation Grants and Projects -- Memoranda and Program-Related Investment Report, 1969-1974 (Box 70, Folder 2)
  - Internal History 5 -- Major Program and Policy History -- Memoranda, Reports to Trustees Re: Program Area One and Program for Peace Development (1 of 2), 1949-1953 (Box 70, Folder 3)
  - Internal History 5 -- Major Program and Policy History -- Memoranda, Reports to Trustees Re: Program Area One and Program for Peace Development (2 of 2), 1949-1953 (Box 70, Folder 4)
  - Internal History 5 -- Major Program and Policy History -- Budget Reports and Treasurer's/Financial Reports, 1956-1981 (Box 70, Folder 5)
  - Internal History 5 -- Major Program and Policy History -- Report, "A Review of Progress at the Ford Foundation" by Paul Hoffman, 1952 (Box 70, Folder 6)
  - Internal History 5 -- Major Program and Policy History -- Report, "History of the Ford Foundation" by Oona Sullivan, 1983 (Box 70, Folder 7)
  - Internal History 6 -- Major Program Changes -- International Affairs -- Discussion Papers, Memoranda, Reports Re: Foundation's International Programs and Organization, 1962-1971 (Box 70, Folder 8)
  - Internal History 6 -- Major Program Changes -- International Affairs -- Notes Re: Foreign Governments and Pakistan Program, 1984 (Box 70, Folder 9)
  - Internal History 6 -- Major Program Changes -- Report, "History of the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program" by James Robert Huntley, 1965 December 3 (Box 70, Folder 10)
  - International Division -- Administration -- Report, "Report on Overseas Compensation Review" and Related Memoranda, 1980 July-August (Box 70, Folder 11)
  - International Division -- International Affairs -- Grant Recommendations, Lists Re: Projects to Strengthen International Peace, Understanding and Security, 1961-1985 (Box 70, Folder 12)
  - International Division -- International Economics -- Correspondence, Notes, 1983 (Box 70, Folder 13)
  - International Division -- Program Management Costs -- Press Release Re: Phased Reductions in Expenditures, 1974 December (Box 70, Folder 14)
  - International Division -- Reports, Memorandum Re: Foundation Work in Less Developed Countries, 1967-1972 (Box 71, Folder 1)
  - International Division -- Report, "The Ford Foundation's Program in the Changing Role of Women", 1973 March (Box 71, Folder 2)
  - International Division Conference -- Summary Notes, 1979 (Box 71, Folder 3)
  - International Relations -- Arms Control -- Report, "The Ford Foundation's Program in International Peace, Security and Arms Control" by Enid C.B. Schoettle, 1982 June 23 (Box 71, Folder 4)
  - International Relations -- Human Rights -- Congress for Cultural Freedom and International Association for Cultural Freedom -- Memoranda, Notes, Reports, 1967-1984 (Box 71, Folder 5)
  - International Relations -- Human Rights -- East European Emigre Publishing -- Meeting Agenda, Memoranda, Reports, 1983-1984 (Box 71, Folder 6)
  - International Relations -- Human Rights -- Grant Actions, circa 1979 (Box 71, Folder 7)
  - International Relations -- Human Rights -- Helsinki Watch, 1983-1984 (Box 71, Folder 8)
  - International Relations -- Human Rights -- Report, "Human Rights and Intellectual Freedom", 1978 March (Box 71, Folder 9)
  - International Relations -- Human Rights -- Report (draft), "The International Dimension of Foundation Programs in Human Rights and Social Justice" by Eric Schwartz, 1984 September (Box 71, Folder 10)
  - International Relations -- Intellectual Refugees -- Correspondence with Social Science Research Council (SSRC) and Notes, 1983-1984 (Box 71, Folder 11)
  - International Relations -- Intellectual Refugees -- Meeting Materials, Memoranda, Refugee Lists Re: Vietnamese Refugees, 1975 (Box 72, Folder 1)
  - International Relations -- Refugees -- Memoranda and Notes Re: Cornelius Report, "Mexican and Caribbean Migration to the United States", 1979 April-May (Box 72, Folder 2)
  - International Relations -- Refugees -- National Coalition for Refugee Resettlement -- Grant Proposal, Memoranda, 1981-1982 (Box 72, Folder 3)
  - International Relations -- Refugees -- Refugee Policy Group -- Correspondence, Newsletters, Report, Program Reviews/Summaries, 1983-1985 (Box 72, Folder 4)
  - International Relations -- Refugees -- Report, "Asian Worker Migration to the Middle East" by Charles B. Keeley, 1980 January (Box 72, Folder 5)
  - International Relations -- Refugees -- Report, "International Migration and Refugees", 1980 March (Box 72, Folder 6)
  - International Relations -- Refugees -- Report for June 1983 Board of Trustees Meeting, "Refugees and Migrants: Problems and Program Responses", 1983 June (Box 72, Folder 7)
  - International Relations -- Refugees -- Report, "Refugee Assistance in Developing Countries" by Barry N. Stein, 1984 October (Box 72, Folder 8)
  - International Relations -- Refugees -- Report, "Refugees and Mass Exoduses: The Search for Humane and Effective Policy" and Accompanying Notes and Research by Francis X. Sutton, 1979-1983 (Box 72, Folder 9)
  - International Relations -- Relationship to the United Nations -- Memoranda, Notes, Grant Recommendations Re: Foundation Work with UN, 1952-1984 (Box 72, Folder 10)
  - International Relations -- World Economy -- Report, "The Foundation's Program Concerned with the World Economy", 1980 June (Box 72, Folder 11)
  - International Relations -- World Economy -- Report for Council on Foreign Relations, "The United States in the World Economy: A Fifty-Year View" by William Diebold, Jr., 1983 May 16 (Box 72, Folder 12)
  - International Relations -- World Problems -- Lecture, "Human Rights and Mass Exodus" Delivered by Aga Khan, 1983 February 10 (Box 72, Folder 13)
  - International Studies -- Asian Studies -- Discussion Papers/Summaries Re: History and Value of I.S., 1974 (Box 72, Folder 14)
  - International Studies -- Asian Studies -- Memoranda, Proposal Re: Funding of Stanford University's Center of Asian Studies, 1951 (Box 72, Folder 15)
  - International Studies -- Asian Studies -- Memorandum, Grant/Expenditure Charts Re: Asian Studies at Select Universities, 1975 (Box 72, Folder 16)
  - International Studies -- Asian Studies -- Report, "Ford Foundation Grants and China Studies in the UK: An Evaluation" by Christopher Howe, 1974 July 11 (Box 72, Folder 17)
  - International Studies -- Asian Studies -- "Southeast Asian Studies: Options for the Future" Conference (3/26/1984) -- Agenda, Grant Recommendations, Memoranda, Reports, 1972-1984 (Box 72, Folder 18)
  - International Studies -- Ford Foundation International Studies Projects and General I.S. Information, 1968-1984 (Box 72, Folder 19)
  - International Studies -- History and Tying-Off of Grant Funding -- Memoranda, Notes, Outline Re: International Programs and University Endowed Chairs, 1982-1985 (Box 73, Folder 1)
  - International Studies -- Overseas Training and Research/International Training and Research Program -- Memoranda, Outlines, Reviews Re: History, 1953-1961 (Box 73, Folder 2)
  - International Studies -- Report, "International Training and Research in the Ford Foundation" by Cleon O. Swayzee, 1967 June (Box 73, Folder 3)
  - International Studies -- Report, "The Foundation's Current Strategy in the Support of International Studies", 1967 December (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - International Studies -- Report, "Support of International Studies in American Universities", 1969 March (Box 73, Folder 5)
  - International Studies -- Report, "The Program of Transitional Support to International Studies in American Universities", 1969 December (Box 73, Folder 6)
  - International Studies -- Report, "Report on the 9,000,000 Special Transitional Program in Support of International Studies in American Universities", 1972 November (Box 73, Folder 7)
  - International Studies -- Report, "International Studies Review: A Staff Study" by Elinor Barber and Warren Ilchman, 1979 September (Box 73, Folder 8)
  - International Studies -- United Nations University -- Memoranda, Reports Re: Role and Issues of UNU, 1980-1983 (Box 73, Folder 9)
  - International Studies -- University Funding and Endowed Chairs -- University of California, Los Angeles, 1984-1985 (Box 73, Folder 10)
  - International Studies -- University Funding and Endowed Chairs -- University of Chicago, 1961-1983 (Box 73, Folder 11)
  - International Studies -- University Funding and Endowed Chairs -- Cornell University, 1967-1985 (Box 73, Folder 12)
  - International Studies -- University Funding and Endowed Chairs -- Harvard University, 1958-1985 (Box 73, Folder 13)
  - International Studies -- University Funding and Endowed Chairs -- MIT, 1981-1985 (Box 73, Folder 14)
  - International Studies -- University Funding and Endowed Chairs -- Stanford University, 1966-1981 (Box 73, Folder 15)
  - International Studies -- University Funding and Endowed Chairs -- Yale University, 1955-1986 (Box 73, Folder 16)
  - International Studies -- University Funding and Endowed Chairs -- Duke, Illinois, Johns Hopkins, Michigan State, Midwest University Consortium, Minnesota, 1979-1982 (Box 74, Folder 1)
  - International Studies -- University Funding and Endowed Chairs -- New York University, Northwestern, Pennsylvania State, Washington, Wisconsin, 1977-1981 (Box 74, Folder 2)
  - International Studies -- University Funding -- Additional Information, 1968-1969 (Box 74, Folder 3)
  - International Studies Review -- Memoranda and Grant Recommendations, 1973-1975 (Box 74, Folder 4)
  - International Studies Review -- Reports, 1973-1975 (Box 74, Folder 5)
  - International Training and Research -- Soviet and Eastern European Grants (1 of 2), 1986 (Box 79, Folder 7)
  - International Training and Research -- Soviet and Eastern European Grants (2 of 2), 1986 (Box 79, Folder 8)
  - National Affairs Division -- Program Reviews -- Background Material, 1981 January (Box 74, Folder 6)
  - Overseas Development Program -- Memoranda, Conference/Program Meeting Notes Re: Economic Development and Foundation Work Overseas, 1955-1960 (Box 74, Folder 7)
  - Overseas Development Program -- Notes, Memoranda Re: Foundation Opportunities in Africa, 1956 April-December (Box 74, Folder 8)